<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>FirefoxonTamás K. Papp&#39;s website</title>
  <link href="https://tpapp.github.io/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://tpapp.github.io/tags/firefox/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-02T16:35:37+02:00</updated>
  
  <id>https://tpapp.github.io/tags/firefox/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Tamás K. Papp</name>
  </author>
  <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html">Disabling Privacy Badger</title>
    <link href="https://tpapp.github.io/post/privacy-badger/"/>
    <id>https://tpapp.github.io/post/privacy-badger/</id>
    <published>2017-05-02T16:35:37+02:00</published>
    <updated>2017-05-02T16:35:37+02:00</updated>
    
    <content type="html" xml:base="https://tpapp.github.io/post/privacy-badger/">&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Firefox has been my primary browser for the last decade. I find it very fast and convenient, and use quite a few addons, including &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-gb/firefox/addon/google-scholar-button/&amp;#34;&amp;gt;Google Scholar Button&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-gb/firefox/addon/noscript/?src=search&amp;#34;&amp;gt;NoScript&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;,  and &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ublock-origin/&amp;#34;&amp;gt;uBlock Origin&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I can&amp;amp;rsquo;t recall exactly when, but about half a year ago various sites started to break. I have not bothered to debug what&amp;amp;rsquo;s happening, suspecting it was was a combination of various plugins, but continued to use Firefox and installed &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://github.com/darktrojan/openwith&amp;#34;&amp;gt;openwith&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; to open broken pages in Chromium (yes, I know, the ultimate kludge). More sites became broken, and I found that now I am spending 99% of my time in Chromium, which I don&amp;amp;rsquo;t like that much, but moreover, it is a resource hog: while using the plugins above I can get the CPU load of Firefox to around 1&amp;amp;ndash;2% when I am not using it, Chromium drains my laptop battery in effectively half the time. To make things worse, Chromium apparently can&amp;amp;rsquo;t open links in the background like Firefox, and insists on raising the window every time I open a link from another process, which is distracting.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Finally, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://discourse.julialang.org/&amp;#34;&amp;gt;Julia&amp;amp;rsquo;s Discourse forum&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; started showing up empty, which was the last straw and I went through my plugins. It turns out hat &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://www.eff.org/privacybadger&amp;#34;&amp;gt;Privacy Badger&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; was responsible for everything: apparently it relies on heavy-handed heuristics and breaks a lot of webpages. One can report this, but instead of reporting around 10&amp;amp;ndash;20 pages which were broken, I simply removed the plugin. I have a lot of respect for what the Electronic Frontier Foundation does, but I am not sure that this plugin is very useful.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;So finally I got back the web the way I like it. Moral of the story: temporary workarounds become permanent, and bite back.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
